Cruise. Kidman. Kubrick.
Eyes Wide Shut is a drama, thriller, mystery film directed by Stanley Kubrick.
Bill Harford's wife, Alice, admits to having sexual fantasies about a man she
met, Bill becomes obsessed with having a sexual encounter.
He discovers an underground sexual group and attends one of their
meetings -- and quickly discovers that he is in over his head.
Dr. William Harford, played by Tom Cruise.
Alice Harford, played by Nicole Kidman.
Victor Ziegler, played by Sydney Pollack.
Marion, played by Marie Richardson.
Milich, played by Rade Šerbedžija.
Nick Nightingale, played by Todd Field.
Eyes Wide Shut is a 1999 erotic psychological drama film directed, produced, and
co-written by Stanley Kubrick, and starring Tom Cruise and Nicole Kidman.
The plot centers on a Manhattan doctor who is shocked when his
wife reveals that she contemplated cheating on him.
He embarks on a night-long adventure and infiltrates
a masked orgy of a secret society.
It is based on the 1926 novella Dream Story (German: Traumnovelle) by Arthur Schnitzler, and
transfers the story's setting from early twentieth-century Vienna to 1990s New York City.
Kubrick obtained the filming rights for Dream Story in the 1960s, considering
it a perfect text for a film adaptation about sexual relations.
He revived the project in the 1990s when he hired writer
Frederic Raphael to help him with the adaptation.
An international co-production between the United Kingdom and United States, principal photography of Eyes Wide Shut began in late
1996 in England, with a detailed recreation of exterior Greenwich Village street scenes built at Pinewood Studios.
The film's production, at 400 days, holds the Guinness World
Record for the longest continuous film shoot.
Following an extensive post-production process that began in early 1998,
Kubrick submitted his final cut of the film to Warner Bros.
on March 1, 1999, which was viewed by Cruise, Kidman, and studio executives.
Kubrick died of a heart attack six days later.
Some post-production was resumed the week after Kubrick's death, which led
to some public debate over the film's state of completion.
Warner Bros.
began an extensive marketing campaign to promote the film in early 1999, though its publicity
materials were vague in nature and marketed the film as an erotic thriller.
Eyes Wide Shut had its world premiere in Los Angeles on July 13, 1999, before being released
in the United States on July 16 and in the United Kingdom on September 10.
It received generally positive reviews from critics, and was nominated for numerous
awards, including the Golden Globe Award for Best Original Score.
The film was met with significant critical notice in France, receiving a César Award nomination for Best Foreign
Film, as well as winning the award in the same category from the French Syndicate of Cinema Critics.
It was also named the best film of the year by Cahiers
du Cinéma in their annual top ten list.
The film was a box-office success, earning $162 million worldwide, making
it Kubrick's highest-grossing film in unadjusted dollars.
The film explores themes of new york city, prostitute, based
on novel or book, sexual obsession, sacrifice.
The tone is mind_bending and emotional and intense.